PROFESSIONAL PROFILE

Senior programmer with experience in web development and desktop applications. Background implementing web solutions and customizing open source software for specific use. Extended volunteer work organizing free software communities. Interested in pursuing organizing roles around technology.

[http://gabrielarodriguez.org]

CURRENT PROJECTS

Mozilla Foundation – Software Engineer at The Coral Project, a two years partnership between New York Times and Washington Post to develop tools for journalists to interact with their communities. [https://coralproject.net]]

Engine Room – mentor and data cleaning and analysis support for the Matchbox program, that partner with organizations to give support on transparency and technology. [https://www.theengineroom.org/matchbox-program/]

Internet Freedom Festival – lead facilitator for the Internet Freedom Festival, a 5 days conference for Internet freedom communities. [https://internetfreedomfestival.org/]

PAST EXPERIENCE

Open Contracting Partnership – Technical Lead in the implementation of the open contracting data standard in Mexico City. [http://www.open-contracting.org/]

D.A.T.A. - founded a non-profit in Uruguay that works with open data and transparency in the government. We launched a FOI site in October 2012, founded the main open data and civil society conference in Latin America, and work on impactful civic tech projects in Uruguay.. [https://www.datauy.org]

2014: Fellow at La Nacion [Mozilla Open News, Buenos Aires, Argentina] Trained journalists to work with data and code. Developed system to crowdsource the extraction of information from very dirty PDFs. https://github.com/crowdata/

2012-2012: Software Developer [Analog Analytics, Portland, OR] Developed a Ruby on Rails platform for clients to offer their daily deals. It was bought by Barclays just as I started working with them.

2011-2012: Software Developer [Centerpointe Research Institute, Portland, OR] Helped maintain the Ruby on Rails website for e-commerce.

2010-2011: Software Developer [Cubox, Montevideo, Uruguay]

This is a software's boutique that works with Ruby on Rails. It has many clients in the US and around the globe. I developed web applications using agile methodologies.

2008-2009: Software Developer [Vozmob, Los Angeles (Remote)]

This is a non-profit project building tools to give voice to immigrants in Los Angeles area. Anybody can post media to the web through any mobile device. I customized Drupal and used its modules to be able to post text messages, audio and video from any mobile device.

2005-2007: Programmer / Marketing Analyst [Babeland, San Francisco]

This is a sex toys's shop focusing on women and LGBT. There are physical stores and a big presence on the web. I developed internal application, supported them, and trained sysadmins to maintain them. Also wrote custom integration code between different tools, manage their plone website, including basic maintenance and programming. I worked close to the marketing department managing the ppc and seo campaigns and analyzing web logs.

2005 : Software Developer [Odeo, San Francisco]

This was a startup that builded tools in the podcast's arena. Later it would deliver twitter. I wrote a desktop application that downloads media files from the web. It worked in mac, linux and windows. It was used mainly to download podcasts to your computer. The configuration was set up via the web.

2004: VOIP Project for the US elections [Radical Designs, San Francisco] The intention of this non-profit's project was to encourage people to go out to vote on the US elections. I wrote IVRs (Interactive Voice Response) in perl for Asterisk servers.

2003-2004: Programmer [Netviax Solutions, Montevideo].

This is a software company that focus on travel agencies. I developed a web tool for controlling the tickets process in a travel agency. It was made in java with sql-server.

1999-2003: Programmer [Centro Mac, Montevideo]

This company was programming dvds with interactive content for different clients in 1999. Later moved into the web. There I developed Multimedia CDS in Macromedia Director / Flash. Later started developing software with GeneXus (Visual Fox Pro Generator). Created back-office tools for managing websites we were developing. Software Development for Internet with GeneXus (Java Generator- DB2 , flash). With them I participated in the GeneXus Internet Virtual Laboratory in ArTech Company. I worked testing/researching new tools (for developers) that Artech was developing.

1996-1998: Editor and Tech Support [Giovannini, Montevideo] Editing Mathematics textbooks.

VOLUNTEER WORK

2010-2011: Organizer [Hackspace Montevideo]

Organized and helped to start a hacklab in Montevideo to experiment with new technologies.

2005-present: System Administrator / Organizer [Systerserver]

I participate in the collective that administer the server for the project. Organized the ETC in Romania for 2006 [www.eclecticaltechcarnival.org]. Organized hacking workshops for women in the Bay Area. [https://systerserver.net/]

2004-2007: Counselor [Exhale]

After-abortion counselor

2001-2007: User [Debian]

Participate in the community (through mailing list, advocating debian) and help new debianitas.

EDUCATION

1995-2001 University of the Republic of Uruguay - Engineering Department Computer Science and Telecommunication Engineering

1999-2000 Artech (Montevideo) - Senior Analyst Genexus (Visual Fox Pro, Visual Basic, Java, C++, .NET)